something that I've run into with the
nešto što sam naleteo sa
growing number of single board computers
sve veći broj kompjutera sa jednom pločom
that I have is the inability to power
koje imam je nesposobnost za vlast
all of them right it's always an issue
svi su u pravu, to je uvek problem
so I started looking at DC power
pa sam počeo da gledam na DC napajanje
supplies that you can get for your
potrošni materijal koji možete dobiti za svoj
workbench because these things have so
radni sto zato što te stvari imaju
much amperage so much wattage that you
mnogo struje toliko snage da vi
could plug 20 raspberry pies into the
mogao bi ubaciti 20 pite od maline u
thing and it'll power everything if
i sve će moći ako
you've got the right voltage but getting
imaš pravi napon, ali dobijaš
on to say something like Amazon Here I
da kažem nešto poput Amazon Here I
am on Amazon Canada and I can see the
Ja sam na Amazon Kanadi i mogu da vidim
price is about 120 dollars for an
cijena je oko 120 dolara za
entry-level one now there are some cheap
Ulazni nivo sada je jeftin
ones well there's some really cheap ones
dobro, ima nekih zaista jeftinih
but generally speaking a good one I'm
ali općenito govoreći, dobar sam
finding are gonna be $200 to $400 for a
nalaz će biti $ 200 do $ 400 za a
really good one and you want to
stvarno dobar i želite da
certainly yeah and you do want a good
svakako da, a vi želite dobro
one now
jedan sada
I also noticed like this one here that's
Takođe sam primetio ovako
three hundred and six dollars it's got
tri stotine i šest dolara
multiple different voltages output so
više različitih izlaznih napona, tako
you can have different like I have some
možeš imati drugačije kao ja
12-volt computers some five volt systems
12-voltni kompjuteri nekih pet voltnih sistema
and sometimes I'm doing some other
a ponekad radim i neke druge
things and so something like that would
stvari i tako nešto
be great whereas some of the cheaper
biti veliki, a neki jeftiniji
ones only have a single output so you'd
one imaju samo jedan izlaz, tako da biste mogli
set the voltage and it's going to be
podesite napon i biće
that voltage for everything right okay
da je napon za sve u redu
so 200 bucks whatever what if I could do
200 dolara koliko god da mogu
it for ten dollars just just putting
samo za deset dolara
that out there yeah what if I could do
da tamo, da, šta ako bih mogao
it for ten dollars do you believe it's
to za deset dolara da li mislite da je to
possible is it not gonna be like one of
moguće je da neće biti kao jedan od njih
those fake SD cards isn't now I hope not
one lažne SD kartice se sada ne nadam
that's why you've got your volt meter
Zato si dobio svoj volt metar
because we're gonna find out if it's
jer ćemo saznati da li je to
fake or if it's legit going ready to
lažna ili ako je spremna
this for so how are we gonna do this
ovo pa kako ćemo uraditi
what's one thing that I that I have too
šta je jedna stvar koju sam da imam previše
many of laying around my garage computer
mnogi od njih su ležali oko mog garažnog računala
power supplies yeah yeah how many of us
napajanja da da, koliko nas
have a couple of extra power supplies
imate nekoliko dodatnih napajanja
pulled from old computers and if you
izvukao iz starih kompjutera i ako
don't have you can easily I mean pop by
nemam te lako možeš reći
a local computer shop that does
lokalna kompjuterska prodavnica koja radi
refurbishing or whatever and they
obnavljanje ili bilo šta i oni
probably have a couple sitting in a box
verovatno ima par koji sedi u kutiji
that you can have for five bucks or
koje možete imati za pet dolara ili
something I
nešto ja
but I I have tons of them laying around
ali ja ih imam na tone
so bill here here's my latest pull so I
tako da zakon ovde je moj najnoviji potez tako da ja
pulled this one out of an old computer
izvukao je ovu iz starog kompjutera
here at the studio and I think it's
ovde u studiju i mislim da je
still good it's got some dust and that's
još uvek dobro ima prašinu i to je
all that's all good that's fine that's
sve je to dobro što je u redu
fine
fino
yep that means you use that yep so let's
Yep to znači da koristite taj yep tako da jesmo
say let's plug it in and I just want to
recimo hajde priključite i samo želim da
make sure that it is going to work so I
pobrinite se da će raditi tako da ja
do have a tester for my power supply
imam tester za moje napajanje
itself this is a dr. power - from
to je dr. snaga - od
thermaltake so I can power this on just
Thermaltake tako da mogu pokretati ovo samo
to see power comes good we've got five
da vidimo moć dolazi dobro imamo pet
volts twelve point two volts 3.3 volts
volti dvanaest tačaka dva volta 3,3 volti
eleven point five volts which is the
jedanaest zarez pet volti što je
negative 12 volt right and five volt
negativan 12 volti desno i pet volta
again and it says the power is good so
opet i kaže da je snaga dobra
we're good to go
dobro je ići
so I went out bill and I thought okay
pa sam izašao napolje i mislio sam da je u redu
well this here's a great idea what if I
dobro ovo je odlična ideja šta ako ja
took the fact that this has 12 volts 3.3
uzeo je činjenicu da ovo ima 12 volti 3.3
volts 5 volts snip the cable made some
volti 5 volti izrezati kabl napravio neke
kind of circuit PCB that had a bunch of
vrsta sklopa PCB koji je imao gomilu
you know connectors and things like that
znate konektore i takve stvari
so that I could use this for a new power
da bih ovo iskoristio za novu moć
supply from my workbench so I ordered
snabdevanje iz mog radnog stola, tako da sam naručio
the parts which you have to buy in bulk
dijelove koje morate kupiti u rasutom stanju
because I didn't have any of the parts
jer nisam imao nijedan deo
yet so then so I got like a bag of
ali tako sam i dobio tako nešto
connectors okay you gotta buy them by
konektori u redu morate ih kupiti
the hundred like the like bags of all
stotinu kao sve vreće
the different things that I would need
različite stvari koje bi mi trebale
to make this happen right and then this
da bi se ovo desilo kako treba, a onda i ovo
instead of going and buying a power
umesto da ide i kupuje moć
supply yeah because I wanted I want to
isporučiti da zato što sam htio želim da
tinker I want to I want to say hey I
prtljati Želim da želim da pozdravim ja
made that myself I did not myself and
Ja sam to učinio i ja
then I can be proud of that and and also
onda mogu biti ponosan na to i tako
I wanted to make it so that I could if
Želeo sam da to tako da sam mogao, ako
if the power supply died I could just
ako bi nestalo struje, mogao bih
unplug the power supply and plug in a
iskopčajte napajanje i uključite a
new power supply - here you go that kind
novo napajanje - evo te vrste
of idea so after all that said and done
od ideje tako nakon svega što je rečeno i učinjeno
somehow I mean the the Facebook machine
nekako mislim na Facebook mašinu
figured out what it was I was doing and
shvatio šta je to sam radio i
put an ad up on my screen yeah nice and
stavi oglas na moj ekran yeah nice i
it took me now I've created a hotlink
odveo me je sada kada sam napravio hotlink
for u cat v dot TV slash ATX and Bill
za u cat v dot TV slash ATX i Bill
are you ready for this
jeste li spremni za ovo
he's practically hiding I'm gonna show
praktično se krije da ću pokazati
you don't worry sweet sweet so thinking
ti ne brini slatko tako razmišljajući
along the lines of what what it is that
po uzoru na ono što je to
I had intended on doing this has an ATX
Imao sam namjeru da ovo uradim ima ATX
input directly off of a power supply it
ulaz direktno iz napajanja
has a power switch to turn it on and off
ima prekidač za uključivanje i isključivanje
then it's got fuses for each voltage and
onda ima osigurače za svaki napon i
individual power outputs for each
pojedinačne izlazne snage za svaku
voltage that is available on the power
napona koji je dostupan na struji
supply the fuses are a nice bonus it is
dostaviti osigurači su lijep bonus je
an absolutely no I suppose I hadn't even
apsolutno ne, pretpostavljam da nisam
thought of that
mislio na to
everything you need that's that's it so
sve što vam je potrebno to je to
I've got negative 12 volt positive 12
Imam negativan 12 volt pozitivan 12
volt 5 volt 3.3 volts and then you
volt 5 volti 3,3 volti a onda vi
figure out the amperage of something
shvatiti amperažu nečega
like this a power supply and figure 25
ovako napajanje i slika 25
Raspberry Pi is easy hmm 10 raspberry
Raspberry Pi je lak hmm 10 malina
PI's a couple of pine 64's we can do
PI je par bora 64 koje možemo
this right or just if you're tinkering
ovo je pravo ili samo ako promišljate
and you want to you want to mess around
i želiš da se zajebavaš
and I want to plug this in and and we're
i želim da uključim ovo i da smo
gonna see what what happens here go I
da vidim šta šta se dešava ovdje idem
haven't done this yet yeah I'm afraid to
to još nisam uradio da se bojim
touch it okay so is it going to power on
dodirnite ga kako bi se uključilo
when I flip that switch fans started
kada sam okrenuo ventilatore prekidača
spinning light came on so you've got
svjetlo se okreće pa imate
your voltmeter on here and now there's
Vaš voltmetar je ovde i sada postoji
no load so could that be its it just
bez opterećenja kako bi to mogao biti njegov jednostavno
shut off Wow can we put a load on it
isključi Wow, možemo li ga staviti na teret
will your voltmeter put a load on say
će vaš voltmetar staviti opterećenje na reći
the 12 volt well it's gonna put a small
12 volti dobro će staviti malu
low losses as well over it isn't it yeah
niskim gubicima kao i nad njim je ne da
positive 12 so let me let me kill the
pozitivna 12 pa mi dopustite da ubijem
switch and power on
uključite i uključite
it's not enough of a load bill you know
to nije dovoljno račun opterećenja znate
so I would have to have a load on this
tako da bih morao ovo da opteretim
in order to get power coming off of it I
da bi se od nje izvukla moć ja
think it's a great idea we work on it
mislim da je to odlična ideja na kojoj radimo
we'll work on this thank you not today
radit ćemo na ovom hvala ne danas
but if I have so if I have a load on
ali ako moram tako da ako imam opterećenje na
this I think that's probably what's
mislim da je to verovatno ono što je
probably right yeah there's nothing
verovatno u pravu da nema ničega
nothing to pull it is a cool device
ništa za izvlačenje je cool uređaj
we're gonna be looking at this over the
ćemo se gleda ovaj preko
next little while it's gonna save us
sledeće malo, dok će nas spasiti
having to buy one of those kits it's
da kupim jedan od tih kompleta
only $10 and it will work on any power
samo 10 dolara i radit će na bilo kojoj moći
supply I'm gonna let you know bill
snabdevaću da ti kažem račun
what what happens when I put maybe a
šta se dešava kada stavim možda a
couple of raspberry pies on the 5-volt
par pite od malina na 5 volti
keeping in mind that this is not a
imajući na umu da ovo nije
transformer either so they stopped
transformatora ili su se zaustavili
holding directly from a good s'alright
držeći se direktno od dobrog s'alrighta
power supply so if I'm getting power
napajanje tako da ako dobijem struju
good off of this which I am then this is
dobro od ovoga što sam ja onda je ovo
going to have clean power as well that's
i to će imati čistu snagu
one of the advantages to doing it this
jedna od prednosti u tome
way plus then if this dies I can unplug
put plus onda ako ovo umre ja mogu isključiti
it plug it in the power supply so I like
on ga priključuje u napajanje tako da mi se sviđa
that cool I like it
to mi se sviđa
cat5 TV slash ATX put a load on it and I
cat5 TV slash ATX je opteretio i ja
think you're gonna find that it's pretty
Mislim da ćeš naći da je lijepo
cool
cool
[Music]
[Music] \ t
[Applause]
[Aplauz]